Finding Aid for John W. Aldridge papers 1943-2007
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- USIA/ Special Ambassador 1971-1974
  The USIA/Special Ambassador series, 1971-1974 (0.25 linear ft.), contains records documenting Aldridge's 1972-1973 appointment by the United States Information Agency (USIA) as a Special Ambassador for American Studies to the American Embassy in Bonn, Germany. The series includes correspondence relating to the appointment and Aldridge's cultural mission, information on the German-American Writers Conference he organized, program materials, and lectures Aldridge gave in thirteen European cities.
  - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 8)
    - 1972 (Box 8)
    - 1973 (Box 8)
  - German-American Writers Conference (Box 8)
  - Lectures, 11 folders
    - Berlin (Box 8)
    - Barcelona/Madrid (Box 8)
    - Brussels (Box 8)
    - Dusseldorf (Box 8)
    - Hamburg/Luneberg (Box 8)
    - Helsinki (Box 8)
    - London (Box 8)
    - Marburg (Box 8)
    - Paris (Box 8)
    - Regensburg (Box 8)
    - Stuttgart (Box 8)
  - Program Materials (Box 8)
- Writings 1943-2007
  The materials in the Writings series, 1943-2007 (5.25 linear ft.), document Aldridge's scholarly and creative work over a 64 year period. The series is organized into three subseries; publications, projects, and unpublished writings.
  - Publications
    The publications subseries is further divided into files devoted to administrative materials (such as contracts and permissions), books Discovery magazine, essays, and reviews. The publications subseries includes correspondence, notes, drafts, manuscripts for Aldridge's books After the Lost Generation, The American Novel and the Way We Live Now, Classics and Contemporaries, The Devil in the Fire, In the Country of the Young, In Search of Heresy, The Party at Cranton, Selected Stories by P.G. Wodehouse, Talents and Technicians, and Time to Murder and Create. This subseries also includes drafts, manuscripts, and correspondence relating to Aldridge's published book reviews and essays, including some of those for which he garnered significant literary attention, including "Afterthoughts on the Twenties and The Sun Also Rises," "Catch-22 Twenty-Five Years Later," and "New American Assembly Line Fiction."
    - Administrative Materials
      - Contracts (Box 8)
      - Dust Jackets (Box 8)
      - Reprints and Permissions (Box 8)
    - Articles (Magazine Pieces and Reviews) (Box 8)
    - Books
      - After the Lost Generation
        - Correspondence (Box 8)
        - Manuscript, 2 folders (Box 8)
        - Promotions (Box 8)
      - The American Novel and the Way We Live Now
        - Correspondence (Box 8)
        - Manuscript, 2 folders (Box 8)
        - Notes (Box 8)
        - Publication (Box 8)
        - Promotion (Box 8)
        - Reviews (Box 8)
      - Classics & Contemporaries
        - Publication (Box 8)
        - Promotion (Box 8)
      - The Devil in the Fire
        - Promotions (Box 8)
        - Manuscript, 5 folders (Box 9)
      - In the Country of the Young
        - British Edition (Box 9)
        - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 9)
        - Drafts and Notes, 9 folders (Box 9)
        - Manuscript, 3 folders (Box 10)
        - Promotions (Box 10)
      - In Search of Heresy
        - Correspondence (Box 10)
        - Revised Edition Notes and Drafts (Box 10)
        - Manuscript (Box 10)
      - The Party at Cranton
        - Correspondence, 2 folders (Box 10)
        - Manuscript (Box 10)
        - Promotions (Box 10)
      - Selected Stories by P.G. Wodehouse
        - Correspondence (Box 10)
        - Notes (Box 10)
      - Talents & Technicians: Literary Chic and the New Assembly Line
        - Correspondence (Box 10)
        - Manuscript, 2 folders (Box 10)
        - Publication (Box 10)
        - Reviews (Box 10)
      - Time to Murder and Create
        - Manuscript, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Discovery Magazine
      - Editorial Letter (Box 10)
    - Essays
      - "Afterthoughts on the Twenties and The Sun Also Rises", 2 folders (Box 10)
      - "American Fiction Then and Now" (Box 10)
      - "American Literature as a Reflection of American Culture" (Box 10)
      - "Catch-22: Critical Reception and Literary Impact" (Box 10)
      - "Catch-22 Twenty-Five Years Later" (Box 10)
      - "Communication" (Box 10)
      - "Cormac McCarthy's Bizarre Genius" (Box 10)
      - "Fact as Fiction; Fiction as Fact" (Box 10)
      - "Fiction In Search of a Subject" (Box 10)
      - "Hostages to Fortune", 2 folders
        - Correspondence (Box 10)
        - Manuscript (Box 10)
      - "Improving on Alison Lurie" (Box 10)
      - "In Memory of William Faulkner" (Box 10)
      - "Introduction to The End of My Life" (Box 10)
      - "Introduction to The Grandmothers" (Box 10)
      - "Introduction to Hamilton Basso's The View from Pompey's Head" (Box 10)
      - "Introduction to John Horne Burns' The Gallery" (Box 10)
      - "The Irrelevance of Outrage in Recent Southern Fiction" (Box 10)
      - "Little Magazines" (Box 11)
      - "Malcolm Cowley at Eighty" (Box 11)
      - "Miller and Mailer" (Box 11)
      - "New American Assembly Line Fiction" (Box 11)
      - "The New Generation of Writers," Correspondence (Box 11)
      - "No One in Charge" (Box 11)
      - "Note: The New Generation of Writers" (Box 11)
      - "On Norman Mailer" (Box 11)
      - "The Place of Values in Contemporary American Fiction" (Box 11)
      - "Proposal for a National Student Organization" (Box 11)
      - "Speaking of Books" (Box 11)
      - Untitled Essays (Box 11)
      - "War and Contemporary Literature" (Box 11)
      - "William Styron's Holocaust Chic" (Box 11)
      - "World War II and the Contemporary American Novel" (Box 11)
      - "Wright Morris" (Box 11)
      - "Wright Morris Country" (Box 11)
    - Reviews
      - Alley Jaggers by Paul West (Box 11)
      - An American Dream by Norman Mailer (Box 11)
      - American Fictions 1940/1980 by Frederick R. Karl (Box 11)
      - Bluebeard by Kurt Vonnegut (Box 11)
      - The Brigadier and the Gold Widow by John Cheever (Box 11)
      - Celine: A Biography by Patrick McCarthy (Box 11)
      - Closing Time: The Sequel to Catch-22 by Joseph Heller (Box 11)
      - Cold Spring Harbor by Richard Yates (Box 11)
      - The Collected Essays, Journalism, and Letters of George Orwell edited by Sonia Orwell and Ian Angus (Box 11)
      - The Collected Stories of Katherine Anne Porter by Katherine Anne Porter (Box 11)
      - The Dangerous Summer by Ernest Hemingway (Box 11)
      - Deadeye Dick by Kurt Vonnegut (Box 11)
      - The Death of William Posters by Alan Sillitoe (Box 11)
      - The Devil's Stocking by Nelson Algren and Sam Holman by James T. Farrell (Box 11)
      - The Diaries of Evelyn Waugh by Michael Davie (Box 11)
      - The End of Intelligent Writing by Richard Kostelanetz (Box 11)
      - Ernest Hemingway: Selected Letters Edited by Carlos Baker (Box 11)
      - Exile's Return by Malcolm Cowley (Box 11)
      - Genius and Lust by Norman Mailer (Box 11)
      - Great Tom by T.S. Matthews (Box 11)
      - Harlot's Ghost, Norman Mailer (Box 11)
      - Hellman and Hammett by Joan Mellen (Box 11)
      - Henry James: The Master by Leon Edel (Box 11)
      - Humboldt's Gift by Saul Bellow (Box 11)
      - If Beale Street Could Talk by James Baldwin (Box 11)
      - Instant Chronicles and A Mania for Sentences by D.J. Enright (Box 11)
      - The Intricate Music by Thomas Kiernan (Box 11)
      - James Gould Cozzens by Matthew J. Bruccoli (Box 11)
      - JR by William Gaddis (Box 11)
      - Kalki by Gore Vidal (Box 11)
      - The Late John Marquand by J.B. Lippincott (Box 11)
      - Making It by Norman Podhoretz (Box 11)
      - The Man Who Knew Kennedy by Vance Bourjaily (Box 11)
      - My Life As A Man by Philip Roth (Box 11)
      - Of the Farm by John Updike (Box 11)
      - The Old Man and the Sea by Ernest Hemingway (Box 11)
      - Principles and Persuasions by Anthony West (Box 11)
      - The Ragman's Daughter and Other Stories by Alan Sillitoe (Box 11)
      - The Saddest Story by Arthur Mizener (Box 11)
      - The Schatten Affair by Frederic Morton (Box 11)
      - Seduction and Betrayal by Elisabeth Hardwick (Box 11)
      - Selected Letters of William Faulkner edited by Joseph Blotner (Box 11)
      - A Sinking Island: The Modern English Writers by Hugh Kenner (Box 11)
      - The Sixties by Edmund Wilson (Box 11)
      - Something Happened by Joseph Heller (Box 11)
    - Reviews (cont.)
      - Sophie's Choice by William Styron (Box 11)
      - Stephen Crane Edited by Robert Wooster Stallman (Box 11)
      - Success Stories by Russell Banks (Box 11)
      - The Tidewater Tales by John Barth Putnam (Box 11)
      - Tough Guys Don't Dance by Norman Mailer (Box 11)
      - The Twenties By Edmund Wilson (Box 11)
      - The Unwritten War by Daniel Aaron (Box 11)
      - Vulnerable People by Josephine Hendin (Box 11)
      - Whistle by James Jones (Box 11)
      - White Noise by Don DeLillo (Box 11)
      - Why Are We in Vietnam? by Norman Mailer (Box 11)
      - William Faulkner: American Writer by Frederick R. Karl (Box 11)
  - Projects
    The projects subseries includes a range of written materials on a variety of projects in which Aldridge participated either as an author, interviewer, reviewer, or advisor. Records in this subseries include notes and transcripts of an interview between Aldridge and Norman Mailer (related note: the audiotape of this interview is in the audio-visual series in box 14), Aldridge's work as a reviewer for the "MacNeil/Lehrer News Hour," his work for the Michigan Quarterly Review, and his notes as a member of the advisory board for the WETA television program "William Kennedy's Albany," and his notes for a biography of George Orwell.
    - Aldridge-Garrett Interview (Box 11)
    - Aldridge-Mailer Interview (Box 11)
    - American Studies Seminar (Box 11)
    - Bread Loaf (Box 11)
    - Fulbright Program (Box 11)
    - Guggenheim Fellowship (Box 11)
    - MacNeil/Lehrer News Hour (Box 11)
    - Michigan Quarterly Review Editorial Board (Box 11)
    - Orwell Biography (Box 11)
    - Program in Literature and Culture in the Netherlands (Box 11)
    - "Reviewing of Novels," Rockefeller Foundation (Box 11)
    - WETA Advisory Board, "Authors' America" (Box 11)
  - Unpublished Writings
    The unpublished writings subseries includes notes, drafts, and manuscripts of poems, reviews, and novels, as well as for books of criticism and a memoir. While some of the materials in this series may have been published later in another form, the materials here constitute drafts and notes. Among the noteworthy materials in this series are early writings from Aldridge's military and college years, an unpublished work of criticism title In the Company of Lions that Aldridge completed in the years before his death, and his unpublished memoir, Against the Current.
    - "After Television Violence, What?" (Box 12)
    - Against the Current
      - Correspondence (Box 12)
      - Manuscript, 2 folders (Box 15)
        [Restricted until July 1 2019 ]
      - Notes (Box 12)
    - "Alaska Helicopter Hunt" (Box 12)
    - Alpine Novel (Box 12)
    - "American Metropolis in Contemporary Fiction" (Box 12)
    - Bellow, Saul and The Adventures of Augie March (Box 12)
    - Cannes (Box 12)
    - Capote, Truman (Box 12)
    - Contemporary Novel Proposal (Box 12)
    - Contemporary Novelists Notes and Drafts (Box 12)
    - The Day of the Wedding Notes and Drafts (Box 12)
    - "Definitions on a Moral Theme" (Box 12)
    - Early Writings, 3 folders
      - 1943-1948 (Box 12)
      - To Sleep Against the Ground (Box 12)
      - Untitled (Box 12)
    - "England and America" (Box 12)
    - English Novelists Drafts (Box 12)
    - Fables and Fantasies (Box 12)
    - Fleming, Ian and James Bond (Box 12)
    - The Flight of the Lion (Box 12)
    - The Friends (Box 12)
    - Halloween (Box 12)
    - Huxley, Aldous (Box 12)
    - Idea for a Novel (Box 12)
    - In the Company of Lions
      - Correspondence (Box 12)
      - Drafts, 7 folders (Box 12)
      - Manuscript, 4 folders (Box 13)
    - The Laboratory (Box 13)
    - Lawrence, D.H., Notes (Box 13)
    - Mailer, Norman (Box 13)
    - Munich Article (Box 13)
    - Novel Notes (Box 13)
    - "Prodigy" (Box 13)
    - Pynchon, Thomas Notes and Drafts (Box 13)
    - Ravello (Italian Novel) Notes and Drafts (Box 13)
    - "Self Image" (Box 13)
    - The Temper of Place Drafts (Box 13)
    - Three Trains (Box 13)
    - Three Women (Box 13)
    - "A Visit with Norman Mailer" (Box 13)
    - Why I Left America Notes and Drafts (Box 13)
    - "The Writer at the Present Time" (Box 13)
    - Writing Notebook (Box 13)
    - Writing Notes and Drafts, 2 folders (Box 13)
- Audio-Visual Materials 1950s-1995
  The Audio-Visual series, 1950s-1995 (1 linear ft.), consists of audio and visual materials documenting Aldridge's projects. The series includes video of Aldridge's appearance at a conference on T. Coraghessan Boyle, as well as a video of the series "William Kennedy's Albany," on which Aldridge served as a consultant. There are also two audio cassettes in the series, one with Aldridge's 1979 interview with Norman Mailer, and the other titled "Jack on the Death of Cousin." Additionally, the series contains 21 reel-to-reel audiotapes circa 1950s, one of which contains audio of a dinner hosted by Aldridge and attended by Norman Mailer and William Styron.
  - Audio Cassettes, 2 audiotapes (Box 14)
    - "Mailer-Aldridge Tape," 1979 (Box 14)
    - "Jack on 'The Death of Cousin' and Jack with Alexis and Michael Allen," 1969 (Box 14)
  - Reel-to-Reel Audiotapes circa 1950s, 20 audiotapes reel-to-reel tapes (Box 14)
    (labels include "Burlingame," "Canby," "Cowley," "Fadiman", "Fisher," "Geismar," "Marquand," "Norman and Jack," "Styron, Mailer, etc." and "Jack on "Night Beat, April 3, 1957")
  - Soundscriber Dictation Recording Disks circa 1950s (Box 14)
  - Videotapes, 2 videotapes VHS (TM)
    - "A Symposium on Contemporary American Fiction Featuring: T. Coraghessan Boyle, State University of New York College at Potsdam," 1995 (Box 14)
    - "William Kennedy's Albany," WETA 1996 (Box 14)